American Association for Social Security Records 5002
Kheel Center for Labor-Management Documentation & Archives
- Merit Rating in Unemployment Insurance - New York State, 1938-1941 (Box 4, Folder 20)
  Correspondence between Prof. Gray and Mr. Epstein re amendments to NYS Unemployment Insurance Acts, specifically the Young Bill; general correspondence between the AASS and other persons re the Young Bill
- Merit Rating In Unemployment Insurance - Massachusetts, 1939-1941 (Box 4, Folder 19)
  Criticisms by Mr. Epstein of the proposed changes in the Massachusetts Unemployment Compensation Law -particularly the merit-rating plan; the Director of the Division of Unemployment Compensation replied to these criticisms with explanations of the policy; further discussion of merit-rating between Mr. Epstein and Katherine Dolan
- Merit Rating - Sub-Committee on - Personal, Mrs. Epstein, 1940-1941 (Box 4, Folder 18)
  Routine correspondence and rough draft of an article "Public Hails Association's Revised Health Insurance Bill" - no author
- Merit Rating - General Correspondence, 1940-1941 (Box 4, Folder 17)
  includes "The Chamber of Commerce Reports on Experience-Rating in Unemployment Compensation' by Adolph Appleman; Resolution #112 by Rhode Island State Federation of Labor that the AFL use their influence towards repeal of merit-rating laws, and a letter from the AFL urging the same
- Merit Rating, 1943 (Box 4, Folder 16)
  Correspondence against merit rating, and "Greedy Employers Menace Worker's Insurance Funds" by Max Finchter (rough draft of an editorial)
- Merit Rating, 1944 (Box 4, Folder 15)
  Routine correspondence - includes lists of organizations opposed to merit rating, and part of an editorial re merit rating by Harvey Lebrun
- McConnell, Bishop Francis, 1937 (Box 4, Folder 14)
  Anniversary Routine correspondence re twenty-five years of service - testimonial for McConnell
- Lee, Clarence H., 1933 (Box 4, Folder 1)
  Incoming letter to Mr. Epstein proposing a scheme for aiding unemployment
- Mayer, A. A.- Fifty Plus Society (Box 4, Folder 12)
  no date - Incoming letter requesting analysis of accompanying bulletin re the aged in society
- Nation (Editor), 1929 (Box 4, Folder 27)
  Outgoing letter from Epstein criticizing life insurance inadequacies in America, as reported in the Nation
- Mailers Service Co., 1943-1945 (Box 4, Folder 10)
- Magazine - Correspondence, Orders, etc., 1944 (Box 4, Folder 9)
- Lyon, Norman L. (American Association of Civil Advancement League), 1931 (Box 4, Folder 8)
- Luncheon Conference, 1942 (Box 4, Folder 7)
  (Nov. 1942) Correspondence re possible reorganization with other national organizations - i.e. the National Consumer's League
- Luncheon Conference, 1943 (Box 4, Folder 6)
  (Feb. 1943) Correspondence re policy of the AASS on unemployment insurance, health insurance, etc.; correspondence from Eveline Burns, Director of Research, Committee on Long Range Work and Relief Policies, John Corson, Director, of Bureau of Employment Security
- Long, Huey P., 1934 (Box 4, Folder 5)
  Incoming letter re appeal for his platform
- Lists (Exchange, etc.), 1931-1940 (Box 4, Folder 4)
  Correspondence re exchange of subscription lists with magazines and other organizations
- Lewi, Mrs. William G., 1939 (Box 4, Folder 3)
  Outgoing letter, response for information re old age assistance
- Letters - Circulation and Renewal, 1936 (Box 4, Folder 2)
  Outgoing letters of requests for services from AASS
- Leiserson, William, 1933 (Box 4, Folder 1b)
  Correspondence suggesting change in scope of organization to include employment security
- Lehman, Herbert (Lt. Gov. & Gov., NYS), 1929-1941 (Box 4, Folder 1a)
  Legislative correspondence re unemployment insurance, old age assistance to immigrants, old age insurance, health insurance, recommendations for political appointments, and Lehman's support of AASS
- McConnell, Bishop Francis, 1928-1943 (Box 4, Folder 13)
  Correspondence between McConnell and Mr. Epstein; incoming letters to McConnell from outsiders
- Old and Middle Age Employment, 1929-1941 (Box 4, Folder 39)
  Requests from the AASS for information from Mass. Dept. of Labor re "Discrimination Against Older Wage Earners in the Matter of Employment;" a study from Michigan's Labor Dept. re accident rates and age groups; additional correspondence on this topic with other sources; and Epstein's comments on an article: re FDR's pension program
- Proceedings - Printing Cost Estimates, etc., 1942 (Box 4, Folder 52)
- Press Releases, 1941 (Box 4, Folder 51)
  Jan. 1941 Routine correspondence; press releases; short biographical sketch of Harvey Lebrun, new Executive Director of AASS (after death of Epstein)
- Peterkin, Walter G., 1935 (Box 4, Folder 50)
  Letter from Peterkin to AASS enclosing a copy of a letter sent to President Roosevelt re old age annuities
- Perkins, Frances - National Conference on Social Insurance, 1933-1934 (Box 4, Folder 49)
  Much correspondence to Sec. Perkins protesting the exclusion of the AASS from the upcoming February general conference on Labor Legislation; telegrams come from many of the AASS's supporters and members; an explanation from the Dept. of Labor is included; correspondence re a conference on social insurance to be sponsored by the Dept. of Labor and the AASS
- Perkins, Frances, 1933-1938 (Box 4, Folder 48)
  Correspondence between Perkins (Secretary of Labor) and Epstein containing agendas to several labor conferences that Mr. Epstein was invited to attend; topics of the conferences were Safety and Health, Minimum Wages, Old Age Pensions, Unemployment Insurance Legislation, etc.
- Old Age Pensions - Various Schemes, 1930-1941 (Box 4, Folder 47)
  Old Age Security by an Educational Birth Tax - a plan for a Federal Old Age Pension system proposed by Saul Wiland (attorney) and sent to Mr. Epstein for comment; review of Downey report on old age pension system
- Old Age Pensions - Trade Union Pension Plans, 1927 (Box 4, Folder 46)
  Requests from the AASS for information _re_ various trade union pension plans- relief systems; copies and explanations of various plans are included (i.e. Brotherhood of Railroad Trainmen, Bricklayers)
- Old Age Pensions - Relief - Almshouses, 1940 (Box 4, Folder 45)
  A statement from the Governor of Maryland (O'Conor) re the elimination of almshouses -requested by the AASS
- Old Age Pensions - Public Employees Retirement Systems, 1931-1932 (Box 4, Folder 44)
  Requests from the AASS for information on state retirement laws; copies of some state retirement programs are enclosed (i.e. Cal.); a copy of a speech to be delivered by the National Education Association of the United States re teachers' pensions
- Old Age Pensions - Private Organizations, Church, School, 1927 (Box 4, Folder 43)
  A copy of the pension program of the Board of Pensions and Relief - Methodist Episcopal Church - sent to Mr. Epstein; Mr. Epstein's reply is included
- Old Age Pensions - Industrial Plans, 1925-1933 (Box 4, Folder 42)
  Correspondence re pensions plans with General Electric, Central Hudson Gas and Electri Corporation, State Senator Putman (Miss.), Harry Kaplan, insurance analyst and underwriter E.D. Hackett, and others
- Morgan, Gerald, 1938-1943 (Box 4, Folder 25)
  Substantial amoung of correspondence between Morgan and Epstein re social issues; details of various plans and personal; also between Morgan and Solomon Bloom, Acting Secretary after Mr. Epstein's death
- Ohio Federation of Teachers, 1944 (Box 4, Folder 40)
  Outgoing letter re Wagner-Murray-Dingell Bill
- Names of People to Contact, 1943 (Box 4, Folder 26)
  Routine correspondence requesting informational aid from the AASS by various organizations and individuals
- Objects, Activities and Needs of the Org, 1944 (Box 4, Folder 38)
- Nonpartisan Social Security Commission, 1937 (Box 4, Folder 37)
  Final report, sent to Mr. Epstein, of a three month study by the Nonpartisan Social Security Commission, sponsored by the Hearst newspapers
- New York State Injunction Cases - List of No correspondence (Box 4, Folder 36)
- New York City - Emergency Work and Relief Administration, 1933 (Box 4, Folder 35)
  A report to the Mayor (John P. O'Brien) covering the operations of the Emergency Work and Relief Administration in New York City from April, 1933 to Sept., 1933
- National Refugee Services, 1943 (Box 4, Folder 34)
  Correspondence re job placements
- National Lawyers Guild, 1943 (Box 4, Folder 33)
  Correspondence re the AASS analysis of the Wagner- Murray - Dingell Social Security Bill
- National Information Bureau (Mrs. May Harding), 1931 (Box 4, Folder 32)
- National Consumers League, 1943-1944 (Box 4, Folder 31)
  Correspondence re the possible merger of the AASS with the NCL
- National Conference on Social Work, 1944 (Box 4, Folder 30)
  Correspondence re participation of the AASS at National Conference of Social Work
- National Child Labor Committee, 1934-1940 (Box 4, Folder 29)
- National Association of Letter Carriers -Empire Branch Thirty-Six, 1944 (Box 4, Folder 28)
  Correspondence re above's oppostion to a Congressional bill involving proposed changes in the Social Security Act; letter to Harvey Lebrun
- Printers, etc, 1941-1942 (Box 4, Folder 53)
- Old Age Pensions - Human Interest, 1941-1942 (Box 4, Folder 41)
  Copies of letters from recipients of Old Age Assistance in New York and New Jersey expressing their gratitude for the payments
- Simkhovitch, Mrs. Mary, 1929-1943 (Box 5, Folder 9)
  Letters to Simkhovitch, President of the National Public Housing Conference, largely from officials of the AASS requesting her opinions and information; her own requests and replies are included
- Raushenbush, Paul, 1933 (Box 5, Folder 1)
  Correspondence re differing viewpoints on social security bills
- Ticonium., 1943 (Box 5, Folder 19)
  Letters to the AASS from J.J. Nevin, promotional manager for Ticonium, re membership in the AASS and info. about the legislation it has proposed for state legislatures, particularly health insurance legislation; replies from the AASS are included
- Thompson, Mrs. Lewis S. (Geraldine) -Sister of Gerald Morgan, 1941 (Box 5, Folder 18)
  Letters to Mr. Epstein from Mrs. Thompson of the New Jersey State Board of Control of Institutions and Agencies, expressing her interest in the AASS's health program; replies from Mr. Epstein are included
- Taft, Robert (U.S. Senator), 1943 (Box 5, Folder 17a)
  Letter re legislation
- Studybaker, Aaron, 1943 (Box 5, Folder 17)
  Letter from Solomon Bloom, Associate Secretary, to Studybaker of the American Retail Federation re an informal meeting to discuss successor to Mr. Epstein; reply is included
- Stone, N.I., 1933 (Box 5, Folder 16a)
  Correspondence re John Andrews' attack on Epstein and the Association's policies and ideas
- State Legislation - Social Security (Box 5, Folder 16)
  Letters to Lebrun from various stats answering his requests for information on old age assistance programs; responses from Georgia, Arizona, etc
- State Legislation - Dependent Children, 1943 (Box 5, Folder 15)
  Letters to Harvey Lebrun, Acting Director, from various state public welfare departments re his requests for information on aid to dependent children programs; pamphlets and statistics on state public welfare programs from states are included
- State Legislation - Blind, 1943-1944 (Box 5, Folder 14)
  Letters to Harvey Lebrun, Acting Executive Director, re his requests for information on various states' programs for the blind; specific state programs for the blind are described in the letters
- Speakers Correspondence - Health Insurance, 1935-1936 (Box 5, Folder 13)
  Letters to various New York newspapers requesting that they each send a reporter to cover the AASS's Health Insurance luncheon; correspondence with John Kingsbury and Charlotte Carr, featured speakers at the luncheon; correspondence with the Hotel Astor
- Speakers - Correspondence, 1942 (Box 5, Folder 12)
  Letters from Dr. Imre Ferenczi, Patricia Strauss (member, Labour Party), and William Green re statements they were asked to make by the AASS
- Tyson, Dr. Francis., 1939-1942 (Box 5, Folder 21)
  Routine correspondence between Dr. Tyson, professor at the University of Pittsburgh, and Mr. Epstein, a close personal and professional friend, re fund-raising and legislative concerns
- Slavin, Harry, 1942 (Box 5, Folder 10)
  Correspondence between Slavin and the AASS re his attempts to raise contributions and members after Epstein's death - assistance from the UAW seemed particularly pressing
- Unemployment Insurance Bill, 1934 (Box 5, Folder 22)
  Comments on the Wagner-Lewis unemployment bill and federal excise tax on unemployment insurance; correspondence between Mr. Epstein and Merrill G. Murray of the University of Minnesota; additional correspondence from Sen. Wagner and Isador Lubin, Commissioner of Labor Statistics
- Sansby, Charles (Box 5, Folder 8a)
- Saltonstall, Leverett (Gov. Massachusetts), 1939 (Box 5, Folder 8)
  Letter from Epstein to Saltonstall criticizing the implementation of a merit- rating system to reform Massachusett's unemployment compensation law, and urging the Gov. not to adopt it
- Rubinow, I.M. re support of AASS, 1933 (Box 5, Folder 7b)
- Roosevelt, F.D. (Gov., NYS), 1929-1931 (Box 5, Folder 7a)
  Correpsondence re old age security
- Rood, Royal D. (Box 5, Folder 7)
  A letter from Mr. Rood, Attorney at Law, enclosing a pamphlet relating to a report in the Congressional Record - no date
- Roberts, Fred, 1932 (Box 5, Folder 6)
  A letter from Paramount Rubber Consolidated, Inc. proposing an old age pension plan that utilizes pension "stamps" issued by the government through the post office
- Review of Pamphlet and Advertising by AASS, 1944 (Box 5, Folder 5)
  Sample advertisement, letters from Advertising Dept.'s of the Nation and the Commonweal
- Reservation Acknowledgements, 1935-1936 (Box 5, Folder 4)
  Jan. 1936 Letters of acknowledgement from the AASS re received reservations
- Requests for Comments, Information, Advice, etc., 1943-1944 (Box 5, Folder 3)
  Questions directed to AASS on legislation; requests for general information re AASS and excerpts from Social Security; also a Conference Calendar for those in the field of public administration
- Renewal Letters, 1932-1939 (Box 5, Folder 2)
  Letters from AASS asking for renewed contributions
- Renewals, 1939-1942 (Box 5, Folder 1a)
- Spayth, George W., 1938 (Box 5, Folder 11)
  Letter from Spayth, Editor of The Weekly Call, to Epstein citing an editorial that he had written on old age pensions for his newspaper, and inviting Epstein's criticisms of it
- Unemployment Insurance - Illinois, 1935-1942 (Box 5, Folder 34)
  Correspondence with Rev. Lawrence - Illinois Association for Social Security- re changes in the Federal Social Security Act, and unemployment insurance in Illinois; correspondence from Peter Swanish, Commissioner of Placement and Unemployment Compensation in Illinois; correspondence with Daniel Goldy, Division of Unemployment Compensation, re the interests and philosophy of the AASS
- Unemployment Insurance - New York State, 1933-1934 (Box 5, Folder 47)
  Letters to N.Y. State union officials from a member of the N.Y. Permanent Conference on Social Security, urging them to write to George Meany (VP of the N.Y. Fed. of Labor and part of a committee to recommend legislation for unemployment insurance in N.Y.) supporting a bill such as the Social Security (which does not use the company reserve plan); correspondence from the AASS re state legislation and its own Model unemployment bill designed by the most prominent experts in the field
- Unemployment Insurance - Hearing on Albany, 1935 (Box 5, Folder 46)
  More requests from the AASS - to the League of Women Voters, etc., - re attendance at the March, 1935 hearing on unemployment insurance in Albany; replies expressing how many could attend were requested; Mr. Epstein stressed the importance of this hearing in demonstrating support for the penc ing Byrne-Killgrew Bill (of which a brief description is enclosed)
- Unemployment Insurance - New York City, 1934 (Box 5, Folder 45)
  Mr. Epstein's opinion on the Municipal Assembly Bill on unemployment insurance
- Unemployment Insurance - Byrne-Killgrew Bill (New York State), 1935 (Box 5, Folder 44)
  Letters from the AASS requesting its delegates to bring as many persons as possible to the hearing on unemployment insurance held in Albany in 1935; major union leaders were requested to do the same (i.e. David Dubinsky); letters from the AASS urging their friends to pressure two particular Senators (Dunnigan and Byrne) for passage of the bill, many of these letters are included
- Unemployment Insurance - New York - Complaints, 1938-1941 (Box 5, Folder 43)
  Letters from dissatisfied New Yorkers who are not receiving the unemployment benefits they feel they should, or have been promised; replies from the AASS - most of which admit helplessness until the state law is simplified by amendment
- Unemployment Insurance - New Jersey, 1934-1942 (Box 5, Folder 42)
  Correspondence with Katherine Wiley of the Consumers League of New Jersey, Vincent Murphy, of the New Jersey Federation of Labor, and others re passage of a state law on unemployment insurance and the guidance the AASS could provide; also, Mr. Epstein's appearance before the Unemployment Compensation Commission of New Jersey in which he outlined many proposals and answered questions; general correspondence with officials of the Commission
- Unemployment Insurance - New Hampshire, 1934-1940 (Box 5, Folder 41)
  Correspondence with Herman Feldman, Chairman of the New Hampshire Commission on Unemployment reserves, re federal legislation on unemployment insurance and New Hampshire's own bill; correspondence with the Unemployment Compensation Division of the Bureau of Labor re reports being sent to Mr. Epstein for comment; related correspondence with Mr. Feldman re his appointment to the Commission and his views on unemployment insurance
- Unemployment Insurance Division - Nebraska, 1937 (Box 5, Folder 40)
  Nebraska. Correspondence re a request from the Unemployment Compensation Division of Nebraska for articles on unemployment compensation laws of the states; reply from the AASS
- Unemployment Insurance - Missouri, 1937-1940 (Box 5, Folder 39)
  Criticism from Robert Cummins, Chief of Research and Statistics on Missouri's Unemployment Compensation Commission over the interpretation of unemployment insurance by the AASS's Social Security; reply by the AASS; criticism of the Social Security review of the Missouri Unemployment Commission from Andrew Murphy, Chairman of the Commission; correction of a Social Security article on the Missouri legislative situation, from a member of the Missouri Senate
- Unemployment Insurance - Michigan, 1937-1940 (Box 5, Folder 38)
  Correspondence with the Michigan Unemployment Compensation re the Majority Report of the Interstate Conference Committee on Experience Rating; also, a letter suggesting the AASS hire Dr. Otto Neuberger for a research position
- Unemployment Insurance - Massachusetts, 1933-1941 (Box 5, Folder 37)
  Correspondence with the Mass. Unemployment Compensation Commission re biographical sketches of its members and requests for info.; Mr. Epstein's criticisms of the Federal Social Security; Act; the AFL's Resolution on Unemployment Insurance (1934); correspondence re state efforts to establish unemployment bills - especially with John McLaren, Chairman of the Workers' Education Council; company reserves plan vs. single state pooled funds is hotly debated in unemployment legislation; correspondence with the Mass. State Federation of Labor - the AASS seding copies of its model unemployment bill to the State House; correspondence with many persons connected to Mass state drive for an unemployment bill
- Townsend, Fr. F.E. (Townsend Plan), 1934 (Box 5, Folder 20)
  Letter from Dr. Townsend, president of Old Age Revolving Pensions, Ltd., asking Bishop Francis (Pres. of the AASS) for his opinion of a plan for universal old age pensions; Francis's reply is included
- Unemployment Insurance - Kentucky, 1938-1942 (Box 5, Folder 35)
  Correspondence with the Unemployment Compensation Commission of Kentucky re free distribution of Social Security; a letter re biographical sketches of the Executive and Associate Directors of the Commission
- Unemployment Insurance Correspondence -New York, 1937-1942 (Box 5, Folder 48)
  Correspondence and bulletins re Dr. William Leiserson's Committee to Study Operation of the Unemployment Insurance Law, of which Mr. Epstein is a member; miscellaneous correspondence with the New York State Dept. of Labor
- Unemployment Insurance - Indiana, 1934-1938 (Box 5, Folder 33)
  Requests for info, from the Indiana Unemployment Compensation Board and comments on the Unemployment Compensation Division's recommendations for amending the state's Unemployment Insurance law; also, Mr. Epstein's opinion of the Wagner- Lewis Bill, and requests for info, by Indiana University on unemployment legislation
- Unemployment Insurance -. D.C., 1940-1942 (Box 5, Folder 32)
  Info, on D.C.'s Unemployment Compensation Act (dependents' allowances); requests for copies of D.C.'s Unemployment Compensation Act as amended
- Unemployment Insurance - Connecticut, 1936-1938 (Box 5, Folder 31)
  A review of Connecticut's hearing on the Commission's Unemployment Compensation Bill and Mr. Epstein's thoughts of the bill; also an info. request to Connecticut's Unemployment Compensation Division
- Unemployment Insurance - California, 1937-1941 (Box 5, Folder 30)
  Letter from the Sec. of the Cal. State Federation of Labor notifying the AASS of Rep. Desmond's attempt to amend the Cal. Unemployment Insurance Act; an article for Social Security describing California's unemployment compensation pro-cedures: correspondence with the Cal. Dept. of Employment also included
- Unemployment Insurance Standards, 1933-1936 (Box 5, Folder 29)
  Correspondence from the AASS to various colleges, the United Mine Workers, Francis Perkins, and others re a tentative set of standards for unemployment insurance established by the AASS's Brookwood conference and embodied in a model bill for unemployment insurance; replies are included
- Unemployment Insurance - Opposition, 1933-1934 (Box 5, Folder 28)
  Criticism of the AASS's old age pension plan system and other public welfare programs they sponsor
- Unemployment Insurance - Laidler, 1930 (Box 5, Folder 27)
  Letter to Dr. Laidler of the League for Industrial Democracy from The Institute of Economics of the Brookings Institution, commenting on his State Employment Insurance Bill
- Unemployment Insurance - Constitutional Provisions, 1936 (Box 5, Folder 26)
  Corrections on an article - "Some Constitutional Obstacles to Unemployment Insurance" - in Social Security (Dec., 1935), made by students at Columbia University and sent to the AASS; a reply is included
- Unemployment Insurance Census, 1940-1942 (Box 5, Folder 25)
  Letters from the Social Security Board in Wash. B.C. containing requested info. on unemployment compensation; an unemployment survey for 1939 from New Mexico; letters of invitation to unemployment compensation administrators requesting them to attend the AASS's Thirteenth Annual National Conference on Social Security
- Unemployment Insurance Census, 1938-1939 (Box 5, Folder 24)
  Letters to state unemployment compensation commissions, requesting they complete and return the AASS's annual census of unemployment insurance developments; requests to the Dept. of Labor for info, on the U.S. Employment Service; also, a copy of the above mentioned survey is included
- Unemployment Insurance - Brookwood Conference, 1933 (Box 5, Folder 23)